YILUN XU

Bellevue, WA • +1 (919) 961-7998 • xuxx0597@umn.edu • github.com/yxx-dev

SUMMARY

Relentlessly curious professional with 9 years of analytical and managerial experience in transportation. Success in pursuing, managing, and delivering sustainable transportation projects that results in carbon emission reduction. Unique combination of engineering ethics, business acumen, and diverse perspectives with proven track records of project delivery. Recognized top performer and leader with bias for action, change, and impact.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DKS ASSOCIATES, Seattle, WA

Electromobility Consultant

June 2022 – Present

- Leading the development of alternative reporting mechanism combining Business Intelligence tool such as Tableau and Web Development technique such as JavaScript, Bootstrap and Search Engine Optimization, strengthening the potential to leverage alternative business model for additional revenue.
- Managed analytical and engineering team to successfully deliver electric vehicle charging evaluation for Bainbridge Island, leading to 2 additional immediate project opportunities with the same client.
- Reduced project timeline by 4 weeks for Kirkland fleet electrification by conducting interactive and realtime data cleaning workshop using Tableau and Tableau Prep.
- Managed fleet and facility data collection process, involving vehicle duty cycle, utilization, domicile location data and engaging cross-functional stakeholders, for zero-emission transformation of City of Tacoma's 900 heavy, medium, and light duty vehicle fleet across five outdated facilities.

Transportation Engineer

December 2019 – May 2022

- Delivered City of Bellevue Green Fleet Strategy that removes 500 metric tons of carbon annually by managing project team, coordinating stakeholders, streamlining fleet utilization data, assessing infrastructure upgrade requirements and developing most practical charging scenario.
- Integrated operational and maintenance cost factors, including energy utility rate structure, into decision-making for most efficient charging scenario for King County Metro's 400 future electric vehicle fleet.
- Introduced carbon credit as a source of revenue to financially justify electric vehicle charger deployment on University of California, Davis campus.
- Strengthened DKS's new electro-mobility business line by bringing team with unique combination of business, engineering and client experience capabilities, contributing to 3 recent project wins.
- Received repeated recognitions from client, partners and team members for exceptional performance in managing analyst team workflow and navigating jurisdictions' ambiguous approval processes for region's first complex center-running Bus Rapid Transit system.

ALLIANT ENGINEERING, INC., Minneapolis, MN

Professional Traffic Engineer

January 2017 – November 2019

- Leveraged Geographic Information System (GIS) techniques to graphically communicate complicated traffic control plans for Super Bowl LII resulting timely completion of event traffic management planning in less than 4 months.
- Supported Twin Cities' sustainable transportation initiatives by completing D Line Bus Rapid Transit (BRT) corridor traffic operation modeling, Red Line BRT Transit Signal Priority (TSP) analysis, Route 5 TSP implementation, and Oak St protected bike lane and pedestrian crossing study.

Traffic Engineer I

August 2016 – December 2016

 Prevented unnecessary rework and saved up to 100 consulting hours and a month of project timeline by challenging current processes and automating repetitive volume balancing during advance traffic modeling of \$350 million Twin Ports freeway interchange reconstruction in Duluth, MN.

UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA, Minneapolis, MN

Transportation Engineer

May 2013 – July 2016

- Awarded "University Services Star Performer" due to upgrading campus transit system with no increase in cost through managing origin/destination survey, influencing for data-driven decision-making mindset, leading planning committee, and project implementation.
- Led real-world roundabout experiment and analysis that shook stereotypes and doubled University community's approval rate of this efficient, unconventional and innovative traffic control.
- Maintained campus traffic efficiency and safety during Vikings football events despite attracting 20% more attendees than previous large-scale stadium events by refining transportation management plan.

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON, Seattle, WA

Web Development Coding Certificate

December 2022 (Expected)

UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA, Minneapolis, MN

Carlson School of Management (part-time)

Master of Business Administration

December 2018

NC STATE UNIVERSITY, Raleigh, NC

Master of Science, Civil Engineering (Transportation) and Statistics

May 2013

TONGJI UNIVERSITY, Shanghai, China

Bachelor of Engineering, Traffic Engineering

July 2011

LICENSE AND AFFILIATIONS

Professional Engineer (PE) – Minnesota and Washington Institute of Transportation Engineers (ITE) – Western and Washington Districts (Member) Transportation Research Board (TRB) – Managed Lane Committee (Member)

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Data management tools – Tableau, Tableau Prep, SQL, ArcGIS, Excel VBA Web development techniques – JavaScript, API, Bootstrap, Node, Express, Agile

GLOBAL CITIZENSHIP AND LEADERSHIP

• DKS Diversity, Equity and Inclusion (DEI) Committee, Chair

- July 2020 Present
- Led committee to focus on activities aligned with defined mission and goals, emphasizing relevancy to business practices and developing champions.
- Global Business Practicums in Europe and Asia, Team Lead

March 2016 – June 2018

- Strengthened client commitment by leading multinational MBA team to draw relevant best practices, lessons learned, business cases from successful innovation centers across US and China.
- Effectively supported partner teams' critical decision-makings by proactively leading primary and secondary research under time pressure and competitiveness challenge.
- Served as ally between conflicting team members to offer cultural insights, alternative perspectives, emotional supports and actionable feedbacks.
- o Translated quantitative analysis on retail partners into meaningful insights and business case by leveraging analytical and communication skills, in development of European market entry strategy.
- International Department of Tongji University Student Union, Division Chief March 2008 April 2009